this is a very strange setup
i the last time i was here was before
kovid and so you know the chairs were
much more packed
and people weren't wearing masks while
they were looking at me
this is kind of a strange image like the
camera
people sitting in this far apart way huh
hello welcome
welcome
it's lovely to be here with you all um
it
brings up a lot of memories to be
sitting in this room when i first joined
the monastic academy
we we lived in this building i slept
probably would have been like right over
there on a bed roll
and we would do all of our retreats in
this room so i probably sat like
close to a dozen retreats i remember
just like
one retreat in particular sitting in
that corner and just watching the
daylight come and go
and come and go through those windows
exactly there
must have been about this time of year
yeah so it's
really sweet to be here with you all um
so today i'm going to talk about
pleasure and its relationship to
what we typically call concentration
meditation
what's often known in the business as
samadhi practice
and unfortunately i didn't print out my
notes so i'm going to look at
this ipad but i promise you i'm not like
playing angry birds or anything i'm just
actually looking at notes um
so the reason why i felt inspired to
talk about
pleasure and meditation is
twofold one
i get the sense from a lot of people
that
meditation practice for them is not
pleasurable
in fact is often experienced as a kind
of slog or
a painful experience full of
physical emotional psychological
distress which
beautiful like it's good to experience
and encounter the pain in our lives
that's very worthwhile um
and yet we can develop this capacity to
nourish ourselves to create kind of
cultivate a sense of pleasure in our
practice so that's one reason
and the other was that this is what i i
recently sat at 75 day retreat
at the monastic academy and this is
mostly what i did was
i sat in the way that i'm going to be
sharing with you
that's specifically um to
cultivate pleasure hi buddies welcome
hello
hello welcome thanks for coming
um yeah
so um so
before i get into the kind of the the
technique and the way of approaching
pleasure and meditation that i want to
talk about i first want to
talk a little bit about like one of the
common frames for meditation
often we talk about concentration
and that is typically
thought to be a translation of the word
samadhi
so you if you've hung out in buddhist
circles or meditation circles really
very much at all you will have heard the
word samadhi if you haven't heard that
word then then
kind of just let this go over your head
it doesn't really make a difference it's
mostly for folks who have
played in these circles a lot just to
kind of trouble
some of the definitions that you might
have grown accustomed to
and so samadhi the act the etymology of
it
means to collect or to bring together
and it's interesting that it's usually
translated as concentration i think
because for us in our culture
concentration has a very particular kind
of flavor
for me like it brings to mind being in
high school or middle school and having
the teacher like
tell me to concentrate which usually
meant like get really focused
on this thing usually a thing i didn't
actually want to focus on
right it felt like oh i have to
concentrate
i don't really want to but i have to
like force my mind
to pay attention in a very narrow way to
this
something like it's like a book or a
math problem
or whatever it is
and so i want to suggest a way of
relating to this word samadhi that has
more to do
with cultivating a state of
harmony to relate to it more
as generating a state of
well-being and ease in
the body and the mind the sense of
bringing together
the body the mind the energy of the body
into a state of harmonious ease
well-being nourishment
feeling of safety um that kind of thing
and so my sense based on my research and
you know what i've explored in my own
practice is that in fact this is what
the buddha was talking about when he
talked about
concentration practice or samadhi
practice and
uh he said in fact in in in the senuta
nikaya
the kind of like one of the holy texts
of buddhism you might say
that concentration or samadhi practice
has
pleasure as its prerequisite and now
the buddha was you know didn't mess
around when it comes to causality he
wasn't being like
like arbitrary about the relationship
between pleasure and concentration there
he was saying
very clearly that you can't
actually get into states of samadhi
without pleasure
that's the proximate cause you might say
of concentration
it's actually not hard to even have like
a kind of
almost like a psychological or an
evolutionary frame on this right so
we enjoy paying attention to things that
are pleasurable
right i like it you know right
you know it's like it's like you like to
give your attention to things that are
pleasurable and so
if you can give your attention to
something that's pleasurable your
attention will tend to stay there
and and in fact this is what happens in
like deep states of concentration is
that there's a kind of feedback loop
between the pleasure you get from paying
attention
to end the like kind of um the settling
in on that pleasure and it just starts
to
feed back into itself and you get more
and more sort of steeped
more and more you let go into that
well-being into that pleasure until it
becomes your whole world essentially and
then
you know i mean it's very it can be
extremely pleasurable
and so um in fact there was
another uh suta where the
the so i this is a little bit of this is
to kind of deconstruct people's
views that meditation like maybe you may
not have this view but the meditation
ought to be painful
that perhaps i'm not really meditating
unless i'm encountering
emotional physical psychological pain
you may not have that view
that's great you may have that view in
which case
i'd like to read you this which is from
the deegan nikaya 29 24
it says so if the wanderers from the
other sects
should say that the followers of the
sakya and the followers of the buddha
are addicted to these four forms of
pleasure seeking that is
states of samadhi states of
concentration they should be told
yes for they would be speaking correctly
about you
they would not be slandering you with
false or untrue statements
addicted addicted to this form of
pleasure seeking
what kind of pleasure seeking the
pleasure that comes from states of
samadhi states of this
harmonious unification of body
mind and attention so he's being very
clear
that it's advisable
it's you i mean he says you should be
addicted
to this kind of pleasure that's pretty
strong word that's pretty strong
language
um
so
so let um talk so i'll talk a little bit
more about
like how to understand this kind of
harmonization practice
and i'm getting a lot of this
framing from a teacher named rob berbea
he
was one of my primary teachers he passed
away recently
but i've found a couple of quotes of his
that
speak i think quite beautifully to this
way of approaching the practice
okay so he says
um samadhi that collectedness
that calm that concentration it leads to
pleasure
it leads to happiness it's supposed to
lead to pleasure
a sense of well-being a sense of
happiness this is
what we are aiming towards and more and
more over time
a really deep sense of pleasure and
happiness and well-being
really deep profound more profound
i would easily wager than anything one
has known before
again strong words he goes on says
it's a kind of harmonization if i can
use that word of the energies of the
body and mind
they come into alignment there's some
kind of sense of well-being
some kind of sense of well-being that
pervades the whole body space
it doesn't have to be very dramatic but
the experience of the body in states of
samadhi is not so much
an experience of bones and fingers and
nerves and what we all know very well
about the anatomy and the physiology of
the body
instead it's an experience of if i can
use this word of the energy body
this feels this space here that i call
my body
begins to feel like a field of energy
it's that i don't mean to make such a
big deal out of this concept that comes
into a kind of wholeness and alignment
and harmonization
and some degree of well-being and so
i would invite you to close your eyes
right now
and tune in to your body
and use your intention to relax
as much as possible
and see if you can
sense your body as a field of energy
see if that's available
almost like a field of tone or
texture vibration
you might if you find it hard to feel
shift your attention to your hands often
you can feel energy there more easily
again one of the ways that we obstruct
perceiving this is through muscular
tension
so anytime you can relax that tends to
make
this sense of the body more available
so do people were people able you open
your eyes now if you're
not too far into samadhi uh you get a
sense of it like just
it's not like not like some esoteric
thing
that's being talked about right so it's
just
this a different way of sensing this
thing we call a body
and that's the thing that comes into a
state of
harmony and alignment in the practice of
samadhi
anybody have any questions so far is
this pretty clear
i can't quite tell from being clear yeah
yeah okay
so all this to say you are allowed to
feel pleasure in meditation
it's okay if practice feels good
even really good even really really good
it's totally okay and in fact um it's
advisable according to the buddha
and it's totally trainable it's
absolutely available to everybody here
to be able to if you want sit down
and pretty reliably experience
states of profound pleasure really is
available to everyone here
just as the capacity to encounter deep
pain with equanimity and poise
is also available to everybody here
practice is a very broad territory
and here i'm talking about one specific
approach
that i've found very valuable that's not
to denigrate encountering pain
and being with pain being with suffering
that's beautiful but
so is cultivating a sense of well-being
and nourishment in the body
so another another quote um
and it says uh this is again rob barbaia
he says
yes i'm concentrating on it yes i'm
focusing on it
but i want to relish it i want to
maximize my enjoyment
moment after moment where is the
enjoyment here
am i letting myself enjoy it can i enjoy
it
this is the part i really like like
nuzzling into it
oh yeah or putting your tongue in a
little cup of honey
and just wanting to lick every last bit
of honey out of it
there's a part i builded don't
underestimate how much we prevent
ourselves from enjoying
at all kinds of levels and through all
kinds of indoctrination
psychologically socially culturally
somatically concentrate sure
but probe and really enjoy enjoy
again and again and again samadhi is
about having a really good time
samadhi is about having a really good
time
yes that's right and so this is what i
did for 75 days
on my solo retreat and it was amazing
it was amazing because one i got to
discover all the ways that
that's true i prevented my way myself
from feeling enjoyment
i was like no i'm actually not allowed
to feel good for no reason
like that's somehow like morally wrong
i don't deserve to feel good for no
reason i haven't worked hard enough
i'm not good enough yet i did a bad
thing a while ago and like you know i
actually deserve to feel more pain
first maybe if i feel a lot more pain
then i'll be able to enjoy and feel
pleasure for no reason but not
not yet not yet
and also i later experienced or
alongside that experience incredible
pleasure incredible joy incredible peace
incredible ease
for no reason at all which
talk about something that's totally
radical like how much
money do we spend every day
every week every year trying to feel
pleasure trying to feel
good imagine if you could have it for
free
anytime you wanted you can
you actually can it's like it's you can
we're going to practice that today
that's what we're going to do when we
meditate today
the first i i feel like called to sort
of
uh disassemble some of the objections
that
some people who meditate a lot typically
have about just
feeling pleasure it was amazing i taught
this at i taught this at
maple and there were there was at least
one and i think two people who
got really angry when i taught this
because they were like
no no i can't just feel pleasure
that and in fact what they discovered
was that they had
deep rooted feeling beliefs that said
that you
cannot if you're not allowed to feel
pleasure
and they had to work through that first
before they could simply feel pleasure
you may find that today and that's good
because that
is what you might need to work through
to just feel good for no reason another
thing that i observed and one of the
reasons i loved this practice
is that the more completely that i was
able to give myself
to these states of well-being and ease
and pleasure
the more that my heart felt
safe to open so one teacher that i've
worked with
says that these deep states of
concentration
or samadhi are the opposite of trauma
right so if you think of trauma as kind
of like a chronic contraction
and holding in the body and like a kind
of negative
emotional mental psychological state
these states are
you know if you do it enough a chronic
opening
a chronic kind of welcoming of um
wholesome beautiful states of mind and
energies into the body
and over time like my heart would just
feel safe enough to open and to soften
and
you know pain would come up emotional
pain would come up but it would be held
in this heart of
fulfillment of deep nourishment that
could
and felt totally capable of holding that
pain whereas
when it felt like that there was a kind
of scarcity mentality
it didn't feel like it could right so it
in fact these states this kind of
practice
enables us to more fully encounter the
pain of life
with a kind of poise and balance and
open-heartedness
that we might not otherwise be able to
okay so um
i'll read this one again because i think
this is the part that needs
double clicking again and again which is
uh this is again robert baia
uh maybe most people
maybe most of us need to completely
forget the whole question of
do i have it now am i in or out of
samadhi is this
it and focus rather on enjoying
on just really maximizing your enjoyment
and getting the most enjoyment in the
moment
and developing what needs to develop to
enable you to enjoy it more
and just drop the whole question is this
it
no he's not saying that's always the
case but maybe today in this
little workshop we can play with that
way of framing it
okay great
so i'll say a little piece oh we have
one more person coming
nice um
welcome hello
hmm
okay so um
what we're gonna do is a little bit
different than uh typical sunday sits
it's gonna be a little bit more like a
kind of clinic vibe workshop vibe
in that i'm gonna lead a guided
meditation
for like maybe like seven to ten minutes
to get in touch with this
what i refer to as the energy body
so we're gonna and i'm gonna then we're
gonna stop and we're gonna have a little
q a
just to make sure that's like kind of
everybody
kind of gets that because that's the
basis then for the next
guidance that i'm going to lead and that
will form another kind of
primary piece in this approach to
practice which is
how to relate to that energy body
in a way that brings those energies into
harmony
into alignment through breath and using
the attention
and using um actually conception
uh then we'll do a little short q a
about that just to see like everybody's
got
that and then finally we'll
do a last guided practice where we'll do
we'll use those two pieces to try to see
if we can
amplify pleasure specifically
so how's that sound everybody
good cool okay
hmm
to begin with find a posture of the body
that
expresses a sense of simultaneous
openness and receptivity
along with alertness steadiness
i try making micro adjustments
moving your spine
you can kind of sense there's a tone
in the somatic field of uprightness
kind of verticality
then once you've found that or to
whatever degree you found that
you might just invite your body to relax
wherever you notice any obvious muscle
tension just
let that release into the ground
you might bring your attention to the
heart
area remind yourself
that no other reason to do this practice
than as an act of kindness
kindness to yourself kindness to the
world
see if you can let that sense
of wholesomeness of goodness
touch your body
this is a beautiful act you've been open
to that
then stretching your awareness to cover
the whole field of the body
and a little bit beyond the body just an
inch or two
almost if it works for you the sense of
an egg shape
and permeate that whole field with
awareness
might experience it as a field of tone
texture vibration
energy some traditions they call it chi
prana often called impermanence and
buddhism
just tune in
tuning the radio station the radio dial
to this field
this field of this energy body
not trying to change it or interfere
with it in any way
opening opening
invariably your attention will contract
will get contracted and when you notice
that
simply stretch it back open
to cover this whole field
so
if you notice obvious muscular tension
just relax
again tension
in the body obstructs the flow of energy
the more you can relax your body the
more vibrant
this field becomes
so for all the practices we'll do today
this forms the base
this energy body experience
so take a few more moments to
tune in to become sensitive to this
way of being with the body it's way of
sensing the body
and just release into it
hmm
with this practice it's not at all
important to have
anatomical clarity
it is important to try to
stretch your attention your awareness to
cover the whole space
now
it doesn't have to be clear that you
have fingers or toes or
legs just a field of energy
permeate that field with your awareness
a few moments i'll ring the bell
when i do see
to what degree you can stay in touch
with this energy body as we
move into a little bit of discussion
in fact it's possible to always keep
a little bit of attention there
and it's fun to explore
so um
so this is a chance to maybe clarify if
that was confusing to you or if you had
trouble
accessing the energy body
if you didn't or if there are no
questions we can move on to the next
guidance
but if there's anything anybody wants to
share about that or
accessing that like i feel like in the
morning i just like still i feel this
sense of pleasure because i can hold my
heart it feels like it's radiating out
of my heart
and i you know i'm like laying down for
like 15 minutes i just feel that
but now doing it it's like i can feel
the tiredness of the day kind of
descending upon me
so i don't know how you bring that
energy
up more yeah yeah yeah so we'll we'll
explore that a little bit in the next
guidance
with the energy body if at least for
this part
it's just a matter of tuning in whether
it feels good or bad or however it is
um and so it sounds like you are pretty
have pretty easy access to the
that kind of field but there's a
question of
how to sort of nudge it towards
well-being
when you're in a state of tiredness yeah
that makes sense cool well we'll see
what happens
in the next yeah yeah
everybody else just have a comment yeah
it seems as i'm doing this like um
like uh an eyeball looking in 360
degrees like just
trying to stretch everything everything
it's interesting to not just be out of
like the front facing
you totally yeah yeah i find that i have
to work harder to kind of fill in
towards the back like there's a tendency
for me to want to like
sense the energy in front more
yeah it's good to try to do the full
full 360. yeah
cool
great so everybody feels oh yeah come on
yes there's a way that my sensations
feel vague
and i'm wondering if i mean i can't
know if they can't compare
phenomenologically with other humans but
um wondering if i should be
also reaching for more clarity
and specificity in my awareness of
sensation
or if it's okay to have this kind of
like global
yeah yeah so this practice tends to be
more global
and kind of whole body and sort of
intuitive and
um less concerned with like
some practices are very concerned with
like the particular arising and passing
away of the particular sensations here
we're
trying to get more of like a big picture
just like sense
of the field as it's sort of morphing
and turning and doing its thing um
as you spend more time with this
practice the kind of
brightness or clarity or vividness will
tend to increase
but you shouldn't try to increase it
it will just increase as you kind of
steep in it and spend more time there
and
um you'll find even in this next guided
practice like
it will become more clear as you kind of
breathe with it and sort of like
steepen it and fall into it and all that
yeah but don't don't try to increase
the clarity although sometimes you can
take the image of like
turning up the dimmer switch like you
can just sort of
take that image like i'm going to turn
up the lights
and all sudden it'll become brighter and
more vivid but don't like
try to force it or anything yeah you say
global but it's
the body yes yes yes yes indeed yeah
global to the body yeah not yeah don't
don't put your attention or awareness
like
too far out like more more than like two
inches or so beyond the body
yeah good thank you for clarifying that
yeah
okay you all ready for a slightly deeper
dive
okay drink some water
[Music]
so in this guidance we're going to
again open up the energy body and then
try a number of different ways to
nourish and harmonize and
bring that energy body into
alignment and so
i'm going to give a lot of different
cues and you can
try them all out or you can
find one that feels really like it works
and just do that it's up to you
so
once again dropping into the body
tuning into the body
as much as possible
inviting yourself to relax inviting your
body to relax
and when you feel ready stretching your
awareness
to cover this whole field
of this energy body
getting a kind of global sense
tuning in
just as it is
again when your attention
contracts
stretching it back open again to cover
this whole field
allowing it to be as it is right now
with the sensitivity to the energy body
to the whole body
what kind of breath would feel
most nourishing
most easeful
most supportive most helpful
you might ask this energy body how does
it want to be breathed
right now
perhaps it will tell you
perhaps it won't just
try something you might
try breathing in a long breath
at the belly
see how that feels
experimenting with breathing in whatever
way
feels easeful
nourishing
like it supports the feeling of
well-being
it doesn't have to be dramatic
how does it feel to
imagine yourself breathing into the
center of the chest
sensitive to the whole body
what's that like being curious about
the impact
so
or you might try breathing in imagine
that you're breathing in through the
bottom of the spine
perhaps the breath
comes in the body there and
flows out into the rest of the space
how does that feel
how does the breath want to be breathed
there
or you might imagine the breath coming
in
through the bottom of the feet
and from there coursing up the whole
body
how does that feel
in the whole body
if your attention contracts collapses
stretch it back open to become sensitive
to the whole field
this will happen again and again it's
okay
you might try noticing
how with each in-breath
there's a sense of expansion
with each out breath a sense of
release contraction
how does that feel
or with each in-breath the sense of
energization
each out breath the sense of relaxation
what's it like to tune into that
again one of these prompts might be
very supportive which case you can stick
with that
you might imagine a line of
energy extending
from the top of the head
down through into the earth
to the center of your body
you're breathing up from the earth
through your body
or breathing down from the sky
into the body into the earth
what's it like to play with that
how does that feel in the energy body
noticing whatever is supportive of a
feeling of
alignment harmonization
rest well-being
what's it like to imagine that the
breath
as a quality of love
somehow this breath carries love
with it
how does that feel what's that like
or what's it like to
see this breath as a gift
a gift playing with different ways of
seeing the breath
what supports a sense of harmony
well-being
breath as gift
gift from life
gift from god
what supports right now
soothing the body with the breath
easing the body
energizing the body
caressing the body
loving the body with the breath
what might it mean to love
the body with the breath
so
for the next few minutes
invite you to explore
play experiment
how can you use
the breath the attention
different ways of seeing to
bring harmony bring a sense of
well-being
nourishment
so
so once again um
create a little space for conversation
curious if anybody wants to share how
that was
or any questions um
and then we have a little little bit of
conversation we'll take a short break
in silence and then we'll come back for
a final
period of practice and that'll be
the flow yeah is anybody
question or anything they want to share
that was quite enjoyable thank you
yeah glad to hear it
yeah it really was
yeah i have a body painting
all the
and time my goal is to
not run from it
and and uh so i'm usually not really
looking
for pleasure uh
well i can say with your help during
this little short
session that thing and i was deriving
quite a bit of
pleasure
yeah very nice happy to hear that
you know yeah
yeah giddy up yeah yeah it's wild it's
it
it's like right there if you look for it
yeah
one thing that i know was helpful for
you for
that i sort of like to ask about is like
um when i'm doing this exploration it
kind of seems like
my ugly pleasurable like like
looking for that ecstatic experience
so there's like um i guess the question
is like
what how pleasurable is like the right
oh yeah so it's a very
it's a good question and
what you want to do is just
lean into whatever well-being is present
so
you'll you can run the experiment like
what happens to the well-being
if you're like this well-being should be
more
and you'll find that it dampens it
right and so the way to
towards amplification of pleasure is
through tuning into whatever is present
there's no way to kind of like force it
to be more than it is
except through like giving yourself to
it more completely
yeah um yeah i've spent many hours
struggling with that on a treat
for sure i think to some degree just has
to kind of work itself out in time too
yeah yeah yeah danny
i really enjoyed the enjoyment
cool i am enjoying it
i had this feeling of like because as
you were
guiding it you used some words like
like the breath being love or the gift
or this being an act of kindness
and i feel like in like like
for me and letting myself drop into like
the energy body
and and like doing the breathing that
felt like the right breathing it felt
like such a relief
and it felt like um it just was causing
like tears to come up
like like i was starving that's what it
felt like was like something
was starving and it was like finally
getting fed
um
yeah um so yeah that's good that's good
thank you thank you for sharing yeah
yeah it's beautiful yeah my experience
is that our body kind of knows how it
wants to be breathed and held
and it sounds like your body was telling
you exactly
yeah it's beautiful wonderful
cool yeah i don't think i fell asleep
i forgot
i mean i just and then at the end
it's like i'm here i'm really
present and that was that's always the
goal
so but
somehow i forgot well you know you were
doing the beginning
uh gone what can you say a little bit
more about what you mean by gone
i don't remember i'm not remembering
what happened in between it's like
you're talking about
breathing and then coming back
you notice that if i go to sleep i don't
think so
i don't know i mean so um
you know if you if you fell asleep it
might be that
that's what your body kind of needs
right now
um if
you sometimes i've noticed that my mind
gets kind of starts
sinking and there's this sort of cloudy
fuzzy thing but it doesn't sound like
that was what was happening for you
i didn't even remember
anything at the end
and then you were talking you said the
breathing oh
oh right oh yeah
yeah i don't know yeah wow yeah
sounds sounds interesting yeah it's
interesting
i've never experienced that hello cool
well
okay yeah let's see if it see what
happens next time
very good
and i couldn't find it then
there's like a little bit of relaxation
but mostly the breath just feels
bad breath feels bad yeah
and the tightness
let go and
yeah trying for so long
yeah so um like with with tim's
question the idea is not to have like
an ecstatic experience it's to
sort of like relate
to the body in such a way that it sort
of like
leans towards well-being however much
is possible right now and so
one way to frame it is that we're kind
of like training this
skill of leaning into well-being
and as you get better at that you'll
kind of discover
more of it you'll also perhaps work
through some of the
obstructions to pleasure and well-being
in your energy body
and then you'll kind of build on that
but it's really vital to this whole
process
not to get ahead of yourself in this
process like yes it is possible to have
like
very intense pleasure in meditation and
you work with whatever's present now
by tuning in to whatever amount of
well-being whatever amount of relaxation
is present and letting that be enough
actually just really enjoying that
whatever it is like it was just a
mildest relaxation well-being like
what's it like to like really bask
in that little bit and not
as so often we do and so often i
i did when i was in my cabin retreat
said this isn't good enough
this isn't enough i'm not doing it right
yada yada and that will
that's one of the ways we we tend to
sabotage the
arising of well-being yeah
um shall we
dive in again oh wait no we're gonna
have a little break
yeah so um how do we do this in silence
get some water
go to the bathroom and then when
everybody's returned we'll
we'll go again in this
last experiment this last
period of practice
we're gonna take what we've been playing
with and
focus on a particular skill
that's um tuning in to pleasure
and i'm gonna say a little bit of like
just add a piece of conceptuality into
the mix
that might support you and your practice
and that's
this triple of discernment
attunement amplification
and this is a way of describing how
consciousness
functions one dynamic of consciousness
whereby
one way of thinking of this is if you
consider this energy body experience as
a kind of
harmonic almost like tonal
way of experiencing the body right so
there's like different
vibrations different tones different
things kind of happening some of them
painful some of them pleasurable
some of them neutral one thing you can
do
with your attention is
discern out of that whole mix particular
we might say frequencies
particular tones particular vibrations
and in discerning them you can then
tune into them again almost like you're
tuning the dial of a radio station
or radio sort of trying to
meet that particular frequency that
particular tone
and in tuning to it it amplifies
it it sort of increases in volume in
your perception
this is true you might notice like
um with actually almost anything that
you
experience depending on how you relate
to it
but in this period of practice
if it's available to you if you want the
invitation will be to
sort of discern whatever quality
might be very subtle of well-being or
relaxation there is in your experience
and then tuning into it
which itself is a skill that you can
learn over time
tuning into it and then letting it or
noticing
how it amplifies how it increases
and then as much as is possible giving
yourself to that
again you're tuning into
life in this case we'll i'll be leading
it to
tune into well-being or a sense of like
pleasure in the body yeah
yes and
if you know i start guiding this and
you're like
actually i feel horrible and contracted
and that pleasure is completely
unavailable to me right now
my experience is that like sometimes
i can sort of dive underneath the
contraction and find a kind of quality
of pleasure dive underneath the pain
other times it's more important for me
to just
be with that contraction
in whatever way that you know how to be
with it in a way that's conscious
and kind and um
not in this case amplifying tuning into
an amplifying self-hate
or anything like that so um
you know i'm gonna be guiding in a
certain direction if that's just
straight up not available to you
then don't like hit yourself over the
head
trying to go in that direction when it's
like you're it's not available to you
that makes sense to everybody okay
work with what's presenting itself
now as always
once again finding a posture that
expresses both
openness and alertness
receptivity and
discipline
letting the body release into the ground
completely relaxing
perhaps scanning your body
head releasing any tension
breathing into that space
neck just relaxing
inviting tension to release down into
the earth
shoulders
upper arms
lower arms
hands
chest upper back
inviting the body to
release relax drop
let go
mid-chest
belly especially the lower belly
taking a couple of breaths into the
lower belly and
letting it hang down to the ground
releasing whatever tension that you find
pelvis
upper legs
knees
lower legs calves feet
and stretching your awareness to cover
the whole field of the body
and perhaps a few inches beyond
dropping into this energy body
again breathing
in whatever way
feels nourishing
feels helpful
perhaps asking the body
how does it want to be breathed
perhaps where does it want to be
breathed
where
does the breath want to go
while remaining sensitive to the whole
body
taking this time to
be kind to the body
to love the body
you might recall any
suggestions from the last guidance that
felt
particularly helpful
invoke them again try them again
or you might be inspired to explore
some other way of
harmonizing and
nourishing easing the body the energy
body
it's all good
and for the next few minutes
just explore experiment with this
approach
using the breath using the attention
even using ideas
reminding yourself that this breath
might carry love
or safety
trying that whatever
feels supportive for the next
couple of minutes
[Music]
if you find yourself putting
too much pressure on yourself for
whatever reason
you invite you to
consider that this is really just like
rearranging the couch cushions to
maximize comfort
it's not a big deal
see what might feel nice
a little bit more nice
a little bit more useful
so
now
you can continue that exploration
if you like or
if there is some amount of
well-being or ease
present
you might try
tuning in
to that aspect of your experience
that frequency
that tone those sensations
attuning
opening
to that aspect of your experience
it doesn't have to be dramatic
is it possible to enjoy
whatever is present a little bit more
what would it take
how could you adjust
to enjoy a little bit more
if the well-being wants to
spread
you can let it spread
if it wants to stay where it is let it
stay
not trying to make it be more than it is
but enjoying what is
present
relishing it
basking in it
tuning in savoring it
gives you a sense of
how to relate
even if the well-being is very subtle
can you tune into that
what happens when you tune into that
now
sometimes i imagine myself just falling
falling into whatever well-being is
present
so
if you find yourself
putting pressure on or trying to make
there be more well-being
try saying
to yourself the phrase this
is enough just
this much just this
is enough
hmm
so
[Applause]
i have about like seven minutes or so
for
questions or comments or shares or
anything else you'd like to speak into
this space
that we have together
yeah um
i was experiencing um an openness that
i've
enjoyed before and was upping the ante
there
but i was also experiencing a
discomfort at the same time
and so um it was going with your idea of
increasing this but then was saying okay
what do you do about that
yeah yeah yep
yeah and so um
it my experience of of practice is
one of choice
right and so i want to be able to choose
to amplify pleasure when it's
appropriate
and i also want to be able to choose to
work with contraction
skillfully when that feels like the
right thing to do
and so when that was happening for you
when you noticed that
that was a kind of like choice point
right i would consider that to be a
choice point where you can say like
am i going to lean into pleasure because
that's
for some reason what i want to do right
now or am i going to like
explore this in my belly right and
you know there are many different
modalities you could you could do both
and you could do both sometimes you
might lean into the contraction try to
like relate to that in a way that opens
it up and then
actually the well-being flows more
completely or you could just kind of
ignore it for a bit
you know so you can experiment but
in this in this practice we were doing
it was the kind of correct
move in the context that i was setting
to go up here and enjoy
um but in your daily practice you know
it's
up to you yeah yeah
yeah typically there will be contraction
in the body unless you're
you've had a very good day or something
i guess
an experience that i had earlier in the
day
um showed up
a lot yeah
and so you're experiencing pleasure
and contraction and then this
person it's almost confusing
it's like okay i'm trying to figure out
that um
i don't know what i'm saying except for
our
team is you said go with what is and
that's
yeah yeah and often i find that like
typically when i do my evening practice
i'll sit down and like
intend to do this sort of practice where
i'm
cultivating well-being and what shows up
is like
the thing that i said to that person
earlier in the day that actually wasn't
so nice
and you know how i forgot to do this
other thing and
this pain in my and then i i have
or i i have to work through that and
then the flow can kind of
happen and part of this part of what
ends up being
in the umbrella of skills within
this context of practice is actually
learning how to
more and more quickly more and more
skillfully work through those
obstructions those contractions so that
the flow of energy can really
take over and send
up a nice incentive structure because
the quicker you can
release those the sooner you can just
relax
into pleasure yeah
something that's interesting as part of
my experience
it's like the sense of like
energy swirling or like moving around
huh um and like
um depending on
like which part of my body my attention
is contracting to
when like further expanding it just like
almost takes a life is it of its own
yeah
what what takes the life of the swirling
feeling
in the whole body or in a particular
part it's like
along the central axis mostly yeah
cool and so it's totally rad to just
like
lose yourself in that swirl and just
sort of like
let that take over that's a beautiful
thing to do and
yeah it's fun that's fun
it's cool that's really good i love that
yeah
jeffrey yeah the usual teaching that
i've
heard is that
happiness is usually conditional about
something that you're happy about
so there's a kind of localization of
pleasure and then there's a
attempt to repeat it kind of thing and
that kind of
has an addictive diminishing return
process for pleasure
because as william blake said
he who binds to himself a joy
dot the wind life destroy
but he who kisses the joy as it flies
lives in eternity's sunrise
and usually there's this talk about
clinging
and trying to grasp and that that
causes our contraction and suffering and
so the way you began your talk
it challenges that kind of yeah
and
when you guided us i felt that you were
asking us to
focus on pleasure as you said for no
reason
and that seems to be
like i remember this song by donovan
having it
i think it's donovan happiness runs in a
circular motion
thought is just a little boat upon the
sea
all our souls are deeper than we can see
and you can have everything
if you let yourself be
cause happiness runs in a circle
if you try to define happiness it starts
to
turn into the other thing
neurosis fear of loss of happiness
doubt if you're worthy because it's
slipping away
all these kind of things but from what i
also heard from the yoga teachers is
that concentration is called dharna
and it's the step before dion
which is actual meditation
and then samadhi emerges
from the relation of that practice at
those the highest levels of the
eightfold yogas
according to
so the idea is that
you become absorbed naturally
first you have to make an effort to
become
free of ambivalence and resolve your
will
that's concentration and then
if you are concentrating on that which
is true good and beautiful
it's giving you pleasure then you become
absorbed and you're in meditation
you've lost yourself of i'm trying to do
something
and you've become pure experience
the problem is then usually we drop back
down
and say oh i just had an experience
i want to repeat that where did it go
but the secret is
not to feel you have to drop back and
analyze it
but keep going yeah that's right with
what is
ecstasy it's not sensual pleasure
that's right but it it appears to be
because it overflows into the senses
that's right yeah but it's very hard
people get
it confused if i'm seeking pleasure i
why don't i just become a heatedness
what is all this austerity
simplicity thing of conquering my monkey
mind and the many voices
i'll just enjoy and that will conquer my
that's dangerous preaching
yeah so i appreciate you bringing the
the
hindu hateful bath into it and
um not so familiar with that tradition
but uh it brings to mind so
if you're familiar with in in the
buddhist system the jhanas the four
jannas or the eight genres
one of the qualities of the first genres
is known as pt which is often translated
as
rapture or pleasure and one way of
defining pt
is as pleasure
without the basis of sense contact
right so it's it's somehow there's
pleasure experience in the body
without any kind of external sense
contact
and a lot of the practice that we did
today is a way to kind of like
tune in or learn the skill of kind of
sparking
that pt which when you
learn to do what you're talking about
like kind of not push or pull on it
and sort of give yourself to it that's
how you can start to
push into kind of jonic territory which
is
very ecstatic and very kind of
mind-altering
yeah so thank you for sharing